Harry Partch Collection 1956-1962
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Harry Partch Collection 1956-1962
MS 479
Partch, Harry, 1901-1974
Photographs and Phonographs, 1956-1962. This collection consists primarily of black and white photographs of the instruments that Harry Partch built; photographs of rehearsals and performances of his operas. The phonograph (LP) series is comprised of 8 separate titles released on Partch’s Gate 5 Records label.
0.5 liner foot
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection
Biographical Note
Harry Partch was born on Jun 24, 1901 in Oakland, California. Partch is renowned as one of the 20th century’s most innovative American classical composers. He was one of the first composers in that century to extensively work with microtonal scales, which he wrote exclusively for his custom-made instruments that he built himself.
Both of Partch’s parents were Presbyterian missionaries that lived in China and fled that region of the world after the Boxer Rebellion. His family relocated to Oakland, California where Partch was born. Partch’s parents continued to live as missionaries, which resulted in the family relocating numerous times throughout Partch’s childhood, often in small remote towns located in Arizona, California, and New Mexico. In these small, isolated parts of the country Partch was exposed to various cultures and their music. Partch began to compose music at an early age using standard western tunings. However, he became frustrated by the limited structure of these tunings and began to develop his own methods of tuning which he performed on instruments that he created himself. Partch composed numerous operas, concertos, and various other musical projects using his tunings and instruments exclusively. In the late 1950’s Partch started his own record label, Gate 5 Records, to release recordings of his works and to generate income. Near the end of his life Columbia Records made recordings of his work which resulted in his music being exposed to a wider audience. Partch died on September 3, 1974 in San Diego, California.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 2 Series
Series I: Photographs, undated
Series II: Phonographs (LP’s), 1957-1962
Scope and Content Note
This collection is comprised of photographs of instruments and opera rehearsals and phonograph recordings. The bulk of the photographic materials detail the handmade instruments that Partch created. The phonograph recordings are comprised of recordings ranging between 1956-1962, self-released on Partch’s Gate 5 Records. The collection consists of black and white photographs of varying sizes as well as seven 12” phonographic LP’s and one 10” phonograph. May of the phonographs are autographed by Harry Partch, some with a personalized and dated inscription.
Access Terms
Partch, Harry, 1901-1974
20th-century composers
Music--20th century
Microtonal music
Performing arts - United States
Beat generation
Container List
- Series I: Photographs, undated
  This series is comprised of black and white photographs which are arranged alphabetically.
  - Instruments (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Rehersals/Performances (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Phonographs (LP’s), 1957-1962
  This collection is comprised of 8 phonographs (LP’s), most autographed by Partch, which he released on his Gate 5 Records and is arranged chronologically.
  - U.S. Highball; 1956, Gate 5 Records, 6, Autographed 1956 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - The Wayward; 1956, Gate 5 Records, B, Autographed 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - The Bewitched; 1957, Gate 5 Records, Autographed 1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Plectra and Percussion Dances; 1957, Gate 5 Records, 4 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Oedipus; 1957, Gate 5 Records, 5 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Revelation in the Courthouse Park; 1960, Gate 5 Records, F, Autographed1960 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Water! Water! And Rotate the Body in all its Planes; 1962, Gate 5 Records, G, Autographed 1962 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - 30 Years of Lyrical and Dramatic Music; 1962, Gate 5 Records, A, Autographed 1962 (Box 1, Folder 10)